hello YouTube welcome to the first
project the project brazing game D
project raising session we are
concentrating today on wiki elections
which is Adriel project that he is
starting so a project raising if you've
read it in game B is we are coming to
raise a project like a barn raising so
for the participants that don't have the
project we're here to practice Omega
rule and find the amazingness and the
project and find the ways that we can
help move it forward for the person and
his job is the project holder is to give
us what it aspirations you would like to
get out of it and then listen listen to
what what it is we have to contribute
and as we move forward with these
sessions every week we will figure out
what works and improve it together and
raise some projects because there are so
many amazing projects out there that
this world needs so and there is someone
else joining us he's just not quite on
camera yet so Adria what is wiki
elections and what would you like to get
another session right thanks Julie
everyone so wiki election there's a lot
of different parts to it easiest way to
explain it is probably that it's meant
to combat misinformation specifically in
politics and science but in just your
general news and other areas as well but
it actually focuses to fight
misinformation in politics and science
and we can go into the more depth as we
don't mature so in doing my yeah well
we're not frozen but he is that's that's
the worst person to freeze okay he froze
right while you were starting yes hello
hello we're back for that good old
technology problems Weiss it's not
working so your bedroo we can hear you
now you not hear us this is we haven't
had this much technical difficulty yet
so okay I think I'm bad how
this happens again I'll likes to pair to
my cell phone and see if that helps okay
so I'm hoping it at least covered like
the first very basic intro to wiki
election yeah aspirations okay so first
just as I was going through my
aspirations I felt myself listing a lot
of like the basic stuff that probably
everyone that does this it's going to
have as an aspiration so I didn't do
those under the assumption that that
would just sort of come out naturally
and the two major assumptions that I had
that I just wanted to make sure we're
down or that one if there's any make
major questions or concerns that anyone
has with the project or a certain part
that will get raised anyway and then as
well if there's anything with the for
luck of a better term the business model
I'm just like how things are structured
if there's any major funding
opportunities that I'm overlooking that
kind of thing that that will come out as
well so my aspirations are one where to
focus the explanation as I'm sure you'll
see as we go there's a lot to it and a
major part of the challenge for me is
figuring out how to explain it to get
people interested is that it everyone
that I've ever like sat down and had a
conversation with seems to agree that
it's you know they're a really important
thing and that this seems like it should
probably work but to actually sit down
and have that conversation usually you
know it's 20 30 minutes and you don't
have that amount of time to get somebody
interested you usually next as I'm sure
you'll see as we go through it
Trust is incredibly important for what
we're trying to do and so any ideas for
either things that I can do or the
organization or the project or anything
that you think that either you
personally are concerned about or that
the public might have some concerns and
things that we can do to sort of build
trust that would be necessary for
someone to believe a source like this
and then finally ideas for like the
levels of content needed before
this is ready to really talk about to
the general public which is kind of tied
to the first thing on sort of where to
focus the explanation but then a step
more on what kind of content is needed
is just like text that maybe some clips
of this video okay or you know is it
complex enough that it requires
infographics and that type of thing
alright thank you
and now I'm at a loss or how can you
actually do that but that is the point
of the aspiration so I have written here
is to help you focus your explanation to
explain it to get people interested I
did have a question about that if anyone
else is stepping in and then how Trust
is important is how we need to how do we
get people to trust in wiki elections so
that it's useful
and ideas for the levels of content so
if anyone else has some questions or
comments on that either in the comments
or Eric yeah I mean well I've got a
couple of questions but I mean I don't
want to jump in in front of you Jubilee
if you've got something you go ahead but
yeah I mean I do have a couple of things
so question was when you said explain to
get people interested what did people
entrusted me does that mean people
working on the project people using the
project funding it what is your main
focus for the interest or all of you um
I mean kind of all three initially so
the goal of the project is I come from
sort of the business software world so I
would organize it's sort of like
business project where my goal is to
actually be able to fund it like a
project and it you know paid developers
to for their time that kind of thing so
it's to be able to pay for it but also
even if we got a billion dollars
tomorrow we would still need an army of
people to give feedback because I don't
just want one group of people to give
feedback that will help build their
trust but then if you pick one group the
group on the opposite side will feel
sort of you know justifiably left out
and like their sides not being
represented in the conversation so to
build a full community of people that
are interested in even if not you know
not everyone
the community has to help fund it but
participate in the development of it and
during the early phases there's going to
be a lot of like we're reviewing content
and sort of people chiming in and
actually doing the work that will make
what he let you look hopefully that
answered your question yes yes Eric that
was my only question we've talked about
this a lot so I forgive me but I'm just
gonna I'm gonna start a very sort of
basic level just to be clear that I
understand what it is first of all right
so yeah so I'm guessing this is some
kind of a system of record-keeping of
politicians or promises kept or broken
how they vote in particular you know in
particular policy areas that kind of
thing right so they can't say one thing
when in fact their record says something
different is that it would that be a
part of it that kind of thing they're
feeling a part of it yeah right okay and
the information would be updated by what
potentially any user like a Wikipedia
kind of thing so any user if they find
something out about a particular
politician that they've done they could
update the record of that politician in
a similar way to the way Wikipedia works
okay cut up for a second but I'm pretty
sure I got the gist of is it like
anybody can go in there and add
information like yes yes pedia not quite
one of the important parts is we're
gonna have multiple levels of
verification so that you can't just go
and create you know ten users and they
all go in there and add content and vote
on things there's a level of personal
purification just are you the person
that you say you are but then there's
also some level of like tracking your
qualifications or tracking what you
personally have like said this is true
the best not true this seems like it's
you know where things will end up so
that as you vote on things if let's say
you're a scientist you're then your
opinion might be weighted more heavily
in you know the areas that the human
expert okay so the race sorry go ahead
my girlhood good but technically anybody
can sort of you know sign up and and
take a look but for their sort of input
to be given more weight the more
verification they've gone through and
the more that we can sort of see that
they know what what they're talking
about they have you know weight it will
be it so the waiting would be based on
basically two things firstly their
credentials their expertise in that
subject area and be on previous history
of having made honest and truthful
contributions right is that basically
right is that the idea in my mind those
are sort of two sides of the same like
what are their credentials I personally
don't care if somebody is a plumber and
they're really good at science and they
chime in to the conversation and they're
always right I want that person to have
a spot in the conversation all I care
about
yeah I'm just maybe getting a little bit
too bogged down in detail there but I'm
curious as to how this sort of threshold
system might work you know how many
contributions who judges whether or not
it was a worthwhile contribution how
worthwhile it was you know how are these
things assesses it seems to me that we
come back to at some point someone's
making a decision what about what's
better than something else right right
so a big part of it is it it's meant to
be and this might be too broad it's
meant to be having conversations through
data instead of through words so instead
of somebody just going and typing up
like an essay and saying hey is this
good and then people judging it at the
very core level everything is about what
I'm calling the evidence so if it's
something scientific it's the scientific
studies it's the things that behind this
actually send to each other and read and
review to say you know what's true
what's actually happening then that is
split out into okay here's how we assess
scientific articles but here is what
makes a good scientific article here's
woman it's a bad scientific article here
are the things to to to watch out for
and a system is built to sort of let the
community assess in this case scientific
articles Nam and then in that content
the goal is to sort of have small tasks
where you say okay read through this and
you know
find where the person wrote how they did
they designed their their study okay so
the people go through and howdy text the
next part is go through and just look at
how the person designed to study and say
is there anything missing
no is it so the these people would need
some reasonable degree of expertise in
experimental methodology for example
right otherwise they're on I'm not in a
position to be able to make such an
assessment right whether it was a valid
methodology whether the sample size was
big enough whether there were adequate
controls in the experiment you know all
of this kind of thing you know you need
to have some understanding of how a
scientist likes Roman and that's it
right absolutely and then to help both
sort of validate that and help to
counter bias among all of the things
that the community would be reviewing
there will be sort of tests or fake
articles where it might take an existing
one get through the testing system
exactly like if it's you know something
that you might agree or disagree with
are you more strict on it if you if you
know it's something that you would
disagree with are you more lenient if
you agree with it at the end of the day
that article was created knowing that
it's got a certain problem or that maybe
it's perfect and and nobody should find
a problem with it but you don't know
where your wish when you're doing it
that's well probably one of the main
methods to sort of help both validate
people's you know you say that you know
science and the experimental method
great can you show us here and then also
are you free of bias or you just doing
this to try and skew things to your side
yeah I mean I hear science it is
supposed science is talking about things
having been scientifically proven all
the time right and that's straight away
I don't want to listen to another word
they have to say because if they can say
something like that they have no idea
what science is all about right and so
that's here a segue this lead so this
feeds into the other thing I wanted to
ask you about or mention anyway was your
thinking was the notion about trust that
people need to be able to trust the site
right and so I think transparency in the
ways in which
information is assessed and you know put
up and waited and so on I think
transparency in this whole thing is
gonna be crucial to that thing of trust
absolutely I think there are some
questions in the comments so I'm just
gonna put it up on the screen from yogi
Jonas I don't know how to pronounce
their name but so that takes a lot of
time to see whether some statement
promise was accurate or being kept
I apologize says I'll do X one can only
assess whether X is good after a few
years and then you're correct once a
certain situation happens and there
nesto has a comment as well that I'll
wait okay so that is absolutely true
the first step which we can do on on day
one even during the the election is just
to capture what do they actually promise
because you know two years later you
might hear some perspective I never
promise that well we have you know ten
different videos at ten different angles
in a campaign rally of you promising
that so it's actually collect the
evidence of them making the promise in
the first place then after that the goal
is to track sort of what did they do to
try to achieve that there's multiple
levels of they tried and they failed
well at least you know they were kind of
they at least made an effort that there
may have been things that either they're
in it their lack of skill me I blocked
them or there may have been outside
factors working against them where maybe
the community doesn't hold it up against
them terribly and they said they
actually did did try but this thing over
here that they didn't control stop them
that's still not perfect but it's maybe
better than somebody that got like the
promise and made no action towards
whatsoever or even worse when the other
direction so hopefully that answers your
question we're a we were we distract it
was said in the first place to act as
evidence in case they ever go back on
that and then once we actually have some
information on what the outcome was
start to track both their intent and
then their actual action I love it
because after the first election this is
actually available in politicians of you
like all I have to actually follow
through
laughter you're gonna be more stringent
on what they promise because it makes
more sense to promise less and deliver
or than to promise everything and
deliver nothing exactly this one is
really easy promises to two different
groups because a big part of this is in
an election to be able to just say show
me what every politician believes about
this and then the community has gone
through the content and ideally
summarized okay this person believes
that about health care or the
environment or or whatever and to note
oh this person's actually speaking at
both sides of the their mouths here's
one video they made I'm Tuesday and
here's a video you know they're yeah we
record on Friday very different things
I'm gonna get to our darkness toes is a
suggestion but this is I think very
relevant expecially in game be
truthfulness versus truth truthfulness
is critical to trust which is basically
I'm gonna butcher it if I try to explain
truthfulness and Trust but it's what you
do you believe what you're saying right
do you believe what you're saying when
you're saying it or is it not right why
just because you believe what you're
saying doesn't mean it's actually
accurate and true and so I won't say
which was which because I can never keep
them straight in my head to do with
intent true is verifiable by some
external means right that means that
it's true it's factually true truthful
means that you know as far as you are
concerned what you are saying maps to
what you believe right that's the
reference that's kind of the the lowest
bar hopefully you at least believe what
you're saying
even if it's wrong hopefully you believe
it to say listen this is what I think is
the case I don't know if or absolute law
but this is what I think you know that
is both truthful and true insofar as
you're not making an absolute claim of
truth right right you know for his
project Cuba 2.0 he's got represented
presentational power as dynamically
assigned D assigned by individuals in
real time in different realms of society
so each citizen gets say a hundred
points in the economy et cetera and you
can propagate these points through the
people you know and if people accumulate
those ways up the tree education can
work as a multiplier of those points you
have in the according area
people usually distribute knowledge in
their own I think this is actually after
the five teachers could making another
comment but oh okay so this sounds like
it's a bit like uh I'm not sure if it is
a regular term or if you were just
making it up Julie but liquid democracy
but a bit more specialized like not just
one group of I'm gonna trust this person
with everything but hey that person
knows about science a lot more than I do
I'm gonna trust them but they don't know
anything about let's say the economy so
I'm gonna trust that person instead so
you can split up who you want to sort of
handle your point and then they can pick
their person that has the most until you
end up with one person that you know had
a chain two people trust them with let's
say science is that I think that is what
he is saying if not that's awesome and
that's what we like if you're gonna have
something like a truthfulness site with
meritocracy of it needs to be their
acute oh yeah I'm just
there's two things that slightly trouble
me about this meritocracy I mean in
principle I'm all for meritocracies
don't get me where I'm not I don't have
an ideological issue with it but just in
a practical sense there's there's two
things that bother me about it firstly
and they're sort of opposite sides of
the same coin firstly is there not a
danger at least in the early stages that
well you know well opinioned people with
good sense in that particular area but
with no track record necessary no formal
track record that their insights will be
ignored right because they they have no
obvious credentials to make do you know
what I mean and so they're they're
they're their insights their input could
could be ignored or downgraded down
waited unnecessarily and on the other
side of that coin just because people
have a good track record doesn't mean
the next thing that they're going to do
is be gonna be particularly insightful
or useful right so I I just see some
practical dangers with with the
applicator well with this would the idea
of the system the application needs to
take those into account is what I'm
saying yeah that's also our nestos idea
I'm not necessarily there a question in
there so I understand that it's sort of
like a variant on liquid markers
but yeah well it's just it's it's a
concern that I I did I that I see these
as potential pitfalls of this way of
promotion yeah so part of it is like
this won't actually help people like
it's not gonna help
I guess distribute power or anything
this is purely an information platform
granted you were cut up there again so
one of the the goals here is to not have
this you can't always just say that
somebody is right or wrong like
especially as you start to get into
science versus religion it's more like
what does the the proof show up what are
the actual sides saying and what are
sort of the highest level here's what
the really disagreeing on sometimes you
won't be able to ya know it's very
useful is right it is useful value a lot
of this will have to do with sort of
categorizing what a certain topic is
about and then individual users can say
what they're interested in so like even
with politicians a lot of times you you
know you won't be able to say this one's
good and that one's bad you might be
able to say with a lot of evidence this
one values business this one does the
environment and then you can decide what
you value and react accordingly it's
gonna end up being more involved in that
I'm sure but the end goal being it's not
supposed to say you know that person is
terrible it might say you know 38
percent of the things they say are not
true that's probably not good for either
side but the end goal being to have some
sort of categorization where the goal
isn't to tell you who to vote for and
what the value is to say you know here's
what the community has said this person
values and you know what they do and
sort of what the evidence shows you can
then sort of tell that what you value
and it says oh based on those criteria
other people with similar values have
voted you know have voted the underlying
information in this way yeah if that
makes sense
there's been a bunch of comments but I'm
gonna focus it back to your aspirations
as to how we help him focus the
explanation of what this this is to get
people interested of the language maybe
around it on the power and necessity of
having something for a politics imbd
right to be able to compare politicians
to one another independent of whether
you're right or left or central right
like how do you trust someone and how do
we see the truth in what they promised
without how did yeah anyway I'm not
grateful language so other people good
not the other thing is the trust I think
we have touched a lot on the trust and
ideas for level of content like what can
be on that page so that we we can trust
it cuz I know we've brainstormed that
and talked about it but other people are
gonna have different right a secure
politician and I guess specifically what
kind of content is needed to start going
out and talking to this about people
like at a mass scale right like the goal
is to you know post things on Reddit and
to get feedback the short term is to
possibly have something like a
Kickstarter or there's enough content so
that people can and look at that and say
yeah that's interesting I want to know I
want to make sure that gets built and
we're on a time crunch because there's a
big election coming up that is
world-changing and it needs to I mean I
don't know if it can even exist by it
yeah time in follow but it can with the
right people involved right if somebody
gave you like if somebody if this was
your full-time job if this was you know
if this was something that someone could
help with a video to make it go viral
that would be huge like yeah and if that
were like if that were an option then
we'd focus on making like not altogether
scalable but like a specific prototype
for that to say let's actually prove
some of these concepts build as
bare-bones as we can and just get people
gathering content and and because a lot
of it is just collecting though
buckets of content and saying like what
are each politician saying about these
did these different these different
topics and then displaying that in a
useful way and I'm not very versed on
American like how the actual political
system works I know much more how our
Canadian one does but like I know they
have you're voting for your local
politician and the president I believe I
believe they're two separate so you can
theoretically there's going to be two
people running for president and maybe a
third independent how do you had like
how do we focus on those two people
right now we don't because there's a lot
of people running for the Democratic
side but once that one person's picked
how do you without villainizing Trump
and without you know it like which is
more our side of the pollen political
spectrum how do you get to truth right
and I think a big piece of that he was
having people who are Trump supporters
part of that right and like already one
of those people in how do you draw
people in to work with people who work
with the left right how do you how do
you have both the right and the left
work on truth together on the
underlining truth seeking instead of
with my views all not as like Trump has
literally said this thirty seconds ago
and then like you don't even need to
look back very far to discount what he
said he knows that I mean he does it all
the time right everybody knows that he
says one thing one minute ones that are
different thing the next minute
everybody knows own yet he's still on
the election right it's not this is this
is this is not news unfortunately right
well I mean regardless of what you you
think about Trump you ran a very good
election and if you actually if that was
your side they did a really good job of
countering the claims against Trump like
but my point is you'll say he'll say one
thing about Korea for example one minute
and he'll say something completely that
contradicts there a couple of days later
right and and nobody picks them up on it
so you know part a part a big part of
this needs to there needs to be some
teeth at the end of it you know what I
mean there needs to be a broadcast
network that actually I don't know
the the Lord's those that do what they
say and really shines a light on those
that do not do what they say do you know
does that make sense well this is our
just a passive repository of information
that people can access if they wish it's
not broadcasting in any way sorry we
just cut out for like 20 seconds I'm
just gonna switch my internet connection
all right you search your inter
connection well so and then Eric won't
have to repeat the question of
broadcasting yeah and yoky also says I
can put it up here the train of thought
how do we get enough information about a
candidate for an election that the
person hasn't been in the public for
long ie
Trump in the last election right he has
a different backgrounds right he has a
business background that does have stuff
in the public view of like did he follow
through on contracts did he but that's
not gonna be necessarily be able to be
shown as easily as with the other and
it's just all the way all the way to
frozen broadcast for a moment back and
then put it back in broken promises yeah
I think also like as part of it also
until he gets back is that like we will
promise things and they don't it's like
oh I'm gonna fix the environment because
the environment is important how how are
you actually gonna do it maybe you
didn't because that piece was impossible
but how do you actually ya figure and
figure that out so I'm gonna let Eric
ask his question again about right okay
yeah well no it was I mean I've got so
I've got I've still got I've still got a
bit of a problem with the information
ecology in this I'm not entirely clear
how it's how it's how it stays clean
because on the one hand you've got
people with you know who who may have
useful information to put up there right
which which would be which would be not
only interesting but valuable for
potential for electors to read and yet
they don't have a track record or any
particular credentials in that
particular field of study their
information gets wasted very lightly and
it doesn't you know it doesn't it
doesn't get very high up the priority
list and so it doesn't get seen on the
other hand people with a track record
can post information and theirs and it
automatically gets weighted heavily
because of their track record so I think
that's open to hacking the other thing
that troubles me is that there's no this
is this is what I was trying to say
about this is this is a passive
repository of information right which
people can go to and access but it's not
making any connections and therefore if
you write judgments or broadcasts of its
own right so it's not saying it's not
there's no like banner headlines yeah
this politician tells the truth 98% of
the time or follows up on their promises
98 I'm this way that's the end goal if
they have that right element to it as
well it's not just a passive repository
there isn't so they Broadcom okay yeah I
mean I more think of it as like a
summarization or an aggregate where
those individual pieces of content
they're important but it's less about
each individual thing and more about
okay there's ten pieces of evidence that
agree with this point they've all been
reviewed by experts and the community
and everyone agrees they're good pieces
of evidence they all agree on this point
so that point is the main thing that
gets presented and if you want you can
dig deep right in a lot of sources of
media that we're used to now they bring
out you know an expert which could be
the only person in that field that
agrees with that thing or they actually
could be an expert that everybody should
listen to you we don't really have a
good way of telling the part but they'll
say something you know 38% of people do
X and that's all they say and then
there's some underlying study there that
we as people viewing it or just supposed
to believe and or if we want to go and
validate it good luck with that
Thursday's random number of gnosis
okay's the random number that he picks
is gonna just cuz I like it
although I think it's more of a count up
timer than a countdown timer of like I
say I'm gonna fix the environment to
invite you by the fourth year and it's
like so that's my promise and then once
it hits it it starts counting up like
you're you know for six months behind
and every time you talk on screen it
showcases it's like well you made these
promises where are they where is our
election reform Justin Trudeau although
he didn't promise at this time around so
I guess that's that's for last time and
they got elected again yes
so yours phase and then color-coded
whether they capture broken promises I
think that is in that right we like we
like visual red-green so one of the
things I think it actually got that the
mock-up on the website is for videos
having sort of a second timeline where
yeah you know if let's say it's a
campaign speech and you know for two
minutes the person talks about you know
the the environment whether they're you
know they believe in climate change or
not or however they're talking about it
the goal is what they talk about during
that point in time like if they quote a
certain you know a certain study while
they're talking about that is other
timelines sort of talks about what
they're talking about at that point in
time so again going through that step of
the first goal is the community just
highlights was a claim made here or you
know is this is this just a story is
there something bit verifiable here
right so if 52 percent of people blah
blah blah okay that that's now a claim
like that and then it goes to the next
step or it says okay so what study did
it does that come from - you did to the
ground it might be nobody can find the
study okay that's worth knowing as far
as what we know this doesn't have any
actual textual basis we talk to to that
campaign theaters drown nobody knows 52
percent that didn't come from anywhere
or it does come from somewhere great
let's point to walk to where that is is
that study good right did did it
actually pass what was a properly
designed study and so on
has it since been discredited for
whatever reason if it is good great did
they cite it properly right is it like
yeah the number 52 is in there but it's
three layers down and it's you know not
used accurately in that context so it
lets people tell this story of I guess
that's probably like the truth for the
true versus truthfulness thing where
it's did they think it's true and then
does the community both the the wiki
legend community and the expert
community do they agree like yeah that
that that's true or at the very least
this person seems to think it's true
because they keep saying it and that's
true and then that's available across
all of their videos and you can start to
see what sort of claims did they make
and you can start to get that number of
okay of all the claims that we have on
file for this person 22% of them end up
not being true or not being verifiable
that kind of thing I think you already
talked about if you already talked about
it if you've already answered it if
people can go back and watch it for the
beginning buddy did you who validates
users contributions right we already
talked about this one right right yeah
and with a lot of this I mean I by no
means things that I've got this idea
that could take on all of the very
complex misinformation systems out there
one of the key parts is that system of
kind of intentionally fake news and
faked like big scientific articles
geared to be you know true or not true
or or meet certain crook or criteria but
there will end up being multiple layers
of that and will end up a particular
houses new ideas I'm not so sure what
you know how to use cryptocurrency for
it but that's also like part of it is I
know your projects more very different
than mine as far as how it's been
implemented but having stuff that is
more transparent and more community
driven is people can can already have
trust in that system as they create it
together to say cuz I know you don't
know cryptic weren't like crypto stuff
enough to implement that right now but
other people do right and other people
bring that table and create that within
it yeah and if there ends up being like
a really key thing and that gives the
project I would absolutely want oh I
mean I think they're absolutely possible
because blockchain or whether it's
blockchain or hash graph or whatever but
Kryptos is all about peer-to-peer
verification and consensus reaching
right so and that's exactly what you're
attempting to do is it's create a peer
to be community that reaches a consensus
on information so you know they're
reaching a consensus on transactions
completed you're reaching a consensus on
valid validity of information or quality
of information so yeah I absolutely so I
mean I don't really understand how it
works I have some understanding but yeah
I have a very small nod and to any
extent where because as I'm sure like on
the trust and truthfulness side there's
gonna be a lot of sort of security
concerns with a project like this but
whether just directly you know people
trying to hack it or if it actually
starts to gain steam groups whose goal
is to put things that aren't true in
there to skew things in in their favor
and so it's going to be that balance of
having it's sort of designed to avoid
that and being as secure as possible but
then also anything that makes it sort of
transparent and trustworthy because
those aren't always the trustworthy is a
global you know that has to be across
the whole thing but there's sort of that
balance of security and transparency
it's really enough of it isn't it that's
really it really is the nub of the whole
thing is is the trust in the information
which is on there by the users therefore
the process by which the information is
arrived that has to be transparent and
and secure and hack free because you
know while there is so much power in
politics and so much money sloshing
around in politics the incentives for
people to figure out a way to hack a
system such as this are very very strong
and so it needs to be pretty much proof
yeah yeah yeah exactly
also having one one deposit of
information for things like political
videos for so that they can't be deep
fakes like how snoops I think is one of
the ones that people go to and it's like
what is this thing real
not real happy in one place for it's
like no matter where it is on Twitter
someone else can post it to this if you
like all that's been proven fake or like
yeah that was a given by the election
campaign to us as like the primary video
when it was recorded they can't go back
and say yeah and so having those and
then having other people in the video in
the audience with cameras showcasing
with a tank GPS like you around there
it's clearly clearly real and they're
all doing it right from different a
little bit harder yes there's that part
where it's like yeah that's not a deep
fake we have 12 two different camera
angles from different people like no
it's that one is 100% real and there
there might be some videos now that we
all think are true that end up being
deep fakes so part of it is and this
will end up being a part of it for each
kind of evidence the end goal is to be
sort of world-class in verifying that
kind of evidence so one of it is there's
gonna have to be some systems in place
to spot deep fakes then also to spot if
there's let's say a video on Facebook
and at this point I don't think that
Facebook is likely to play ball so this
would probably end up being like a
browser extension that sees the video
you're playing an ad sort of its own
overlay where it says hey we know that
video here's what the community has said
about that video and you can even do the
the same timeline of oh here's a spot in
DT video where they quote some stat
here's what we've learned about that
stat if it was used honestly if it was
used from a credited source but also oh
the people who you know the people are
systems that specialize in spotting deep
pigs have analyzed this video and it's a
deep fake so for it to be able to say
that on all the videos that it has that
kind of information about alright there
was something that was said earlier that
I think is important i but i don't know
if it's gonna really it kind of goes to
left versus right trouble truth is most
important intense authoring leads to our
tribe must win because this is
existential and then Peter just added
that tribalism is here to stay to make
progress if it were ideas that politics
were centered
set of party lines and personal
occultism and I think having one place
for information again it's not going to
counteract that completely they're still
getting people like Oh for someone just
because they're a woman or just because
they're their same culture and but at
the same time to be like oh they have
read right like one it's gonna help
other people vote for them if they're
green truthful and actually follow
through and they they do this is like
truthfulness are you gonna follow
through on and also are they in
alignment with your values right like
I'm gonna vote for people who are
environmental and social justice and but
that doesn't mean someone else is even
if their truth are truthful right and I
and somebody gives you you know I'm
gonna do all this if I mentally great
one do they have the skills does it
actually seem love something that could
theoretically do it if they applied
themselves and then to does their track
record show they would they're people
who were well-connected and intelligent
enough to solve this kind of problem is
but you're like there's no way they're
going to or I think there will
intentioned I don't think that they like
vid they'll try and they'll probably
fail right if the community feels that
that's important to know
okay I feel like there's something
missing from your statement in the
middle because there was this who would
validate user contribution so we talked
about and your next one is if Adriel
knows that site I just found it I don't
know which one you're talking about
this is evoke so yeah post it and
hopeful I can always send him the link
from here after whatever but I just
don't know what's that you're talking
about in reference to that but any sites
that already exists that are about
verifying information would be very
useful yep and that video only has the
deep into the are yours video will be
almost like paper photographs today
video right it's just a very nice video
is it can you deep fake VR in its like
the other just two different videos one
for each eye that's basically and then
made from a certain camera angle to
support a being like you looking at it
so in theory it might be a little bit
harder but still totally do
deep pickable I would think uh I do
think our minds will be more easily able
to accept VR versus the other one
because you feel like you were actually
there right you're like no I saw the
speech it was like I was there no I'm
still better video tools now the
politics is going in VR whoever said
really released and I don't know if it
is because you do you have to ME baby
because maybe we get to the point where
you don't need special equipment to do
VR but as soon as soon as you need
special equipment to do something it has
to reach the population it has to be
like 80% of people have it right in
order for not to be the the the tool
like even we do have the our televisions
right or like 3d televisions not VR and
they didn't really gain that much
traction like 3d and movies even more
like and you know like it's not as cool
it's just a gimmick believe it if that's
true that it that it does go over your I
don't see as we've just said I don't see
BR being fundamentally different video
exactly there would be some challenges I
guess like with the interface cuz you
would probably have to screw with the VR
and make it kind of ugly or you might
like have a different kind of overlay
then the guys the person is talking you
have some weird like Minority Report
style like a box and then a bubble
coming up there with the stats you have
to figure out how to make it look decent
so they wouldn't turn people off but at
the end of the day it's just another
kind of content you're focusing on VR
instead a video which I think we are
like including it but then also that
real title be the only authentication
method people will trust I'm not so sure
that would even maybe be true because if
your VR is a live stream the same like
being there if they can be deep like a
live stream VR is like oh look I'm in
Paris I know I'm not actually in Paris
so how does that become a verifiable
definite I think there might be some
like as air can to like people might be
more inclined to believe that because
they put on it like I I think I'm there
but really it's just filming it with two
cameras instead of one and it's
streaming it a slightly different way at
the end the whole goal of this is to be
able to do whatever people need to do to
be able to trust information
yep build something from the ground up
the specializes in VR once we are dis
popular or not we'd absolutely do that
that's the end goal for all this this is
just like the the tactics to be able to
get to the endpoint of can a person
trustus do they have enough information
have they seen a track record of the
site not showing biased and saying like
it's agree with me it's disagree with me
it's you know torn down people did like
but it's also turned on people that I
don't like so there's some amount of
okay it does seem fair having all of
that enough to be able to support that
concept of as many people as possible
see it and say I trust that it says like
enough people have reviewed it I can dig
as deep as I want into the evidence that
people use to say it was true or not
there's no hiding anything yeah you
paraphrase a certain stream of data is
being created in real-time using a
crypto like method yeah that will be
powerful and that's where I think having
the base of people that are the ones who
are supposed to trust it I eat all of us
are is important to have that be part of
the system to create it to say hey how
do I trust this right like if you create
something that's absolutely amazing it's
all this information out there people
don't trust it it's not useful and and
part of it is like you it would cost so
much money to do this all yourself right
to put all the information in for one
person or to pay people to put it in is
an astronomical cost especially moving
forward because this is work people will
and want to do for free because they
want access to the information and
because they want to be able to be part
of that trust economy they you know what
I mean that being part of that but then
there will also be people in there that
are there any way you can avoid bias
right is to have it distributed I mean
however well-intentioned one person or
one group of people is I mean however
genuine their hearts are they will have
biases right and the information that
they gather in the way in which it's
real might have biases of cost
the person I don't want any person who
is urgent to say that's true that's not
true
absolutely I want to be able to speak up
for me and my discernment but not to be
propagated everywhere else like Oh like
talking about it has to be video or VR
the whole point is to have as much
content as possible
so it's you can still fake VR you can
still fake like you can't fake once it's
been added to blockchain my
understanding is that sort of a winna
gets secured but if the source that's
feeding it in was like you know some
sort of an advanced live deep thing yeah
that's alright needs to be verified
before it goes into the block drafts if
the like one of the end goals is to have
an app where the community knows one of
the things that we wanted as many
different sources of content as possible
so at the end of the day what I want to
see is if you see any you know campaign
rally there's 30 people in the audience
holding up a phone not that different
from right now but the difference is a
bunch of them are using some app that's
feeding into the same source saying
here's the same thing happening at the
same time from 73 different camera
angles
good luck saying that's fake yeah maybe
of two of them people are being sketchy
and faking it okay we've got two camera
angles where we can you know use
technology to spot how they're fake but
also here's this massive amount of
contents and every camera angle the
audio all lines up perfectly every
different angle agrees with each other
experts have reviewed it and say yep
this all says it's the same thing that's
what that would look like from that
camera angle that's why and I think this
goes to also just what TRICARE is saying
there will be another group of people
who will hone in and focus on those
biases that there will it like you need
that you need people of different prices
for to know Charles Vyse sake different
Hamelin camera angle right they're not
people who do a lot of the work because
they they care about a certain thing so
if you really care about the environment
and that's where your bias lies great go
ahead and add as much of the media
content you want it's still going to
filter through the same systems and
hopefully filter as much of your bias
off as possible but most people who are
like the really sort of neutral and
looking at it from both sides they
aren't gonna be that interested in
solving it like I'm gonna do all this
work to maybe find out which side is
true even though I'm not terribly
concerned I think they'll sort of be
some of the filters but the people who
really submit the content and do a lot
of the work will be devised people you
know I just rewind a little bit you guys
were talking earlier maybe 20 minutes
ago you were talking about seeing as how
there's an actual election coming up in
America very soon it's a shame that
something like this isn't in place for
that right and I think I think it was
you Adriel mentioned something along the
lines of you know be good to maybe just
have one element of it to trial some
sort of thing but what about what you
mentioned earlier on the at the notion
of because this doesn't require any
history at all but talking to one
audience and saying one thing about a
particular topic or a particular policy
area and then talking to a different
audience and saying a different thing
that would be relatively easy to track I
think there must be transcripts of all
of these speech I mean time-consuming
but but nevertheless relatively easy and
that's something that could be done get
started straight away it just needs
manpower and that could be posted
relatively easily and it doesn't require
verification because it's a it's all
transcripted so yeah and and and then
you could as I say you could at least
highlight the double stand at the
hypocrisy the two-faced adness within
the campaign of any image that would be
really helpful for I mean if you need
people to do it and there's only seven
people watching but like right now with
a democratic election with what a
primaries right like like Bernie Sanders
I think has held pretty stru to his
values back to the sixties right like he
wasn't like oops I was I was racist and
sexist homophobic but I've seen the
light and I don't know that that's I
don't think it's necessarily a character
flaw to have been that and now aren't
like I think the changing is something
that's important but that's not the same
as like during this election cycle
saying to one audience hey I'm a
socialist into another audio like
he's we know who Bernie that's right
he's not changing he's like yeah I'm
against for I don't care what more it is
up against it and having that be like
how do I don't know I kind of think of
like Elizabeth Warren I think also has a
more of a track record of but she's she
her history was not democratic right I
think her history was in like if she did
kind of switch sides she was Republican
earlier on did submission like Oh
like sort of to help backup the credit
card companies to help us stuff and she
learned Oh a lot of bankruptcies are
caused by like by medical debt and then
she actually kind of that switched her
sighs she's like oh this is a super
important topic and then started to
campaign against medical debt which is
good to note with I've seen people pitch
that as a negative but I've also seen
people say wait that sounds amazing
somebody read data it disagree with with
what they said and then they switch
sides causes weakness though isn't it in
modern politics if you change your mind
it's seen as a u-turn and it's seen as a
sign of weakness right not having the
courage of your convictions kind of
thing is such all right
well it's a rare thing it depends how
often it happens and what the trigger
was like if you're either going back and
forth back and forth that is a weakness
like do your research if it's one
defining thing if you did your research
you're on one side you said wait a
minute that doesn't line up all the
information is pointing in the other
directions and then you switch once I
think that's a huge strength
all right great I think that shows
character and what's the word integrity
yeah right yeah and so we have about
five minutes left as far as is there
anything else you would like to focus on
or get out of this and then I'm gonna
save the last two or three minutes for
to discuss the process itself okay so I
think a lot of this was just enough so
that you and the audience sort of
understood once you understand so far
where is the best spot to focus like
what could I do that
like what what slice of this could I
talk about to get people interested or
just sort of how everything works
together like there's the
basis of evidence we didn't even talk
about the scientific part where instead
of just assessing politicians the end
goal is also to be able to look at
things like climate change in vaccines
and stuff like that look at all of the
available data have people summarized it
again using that sort of we're gonna
have some fake studies in there and some
fake things to say like okay even if
you're Pro vaccine and the study is anti
vaccine did they design it properly it's
not okay say where they didn't if they
did great you can say they designed it
it it properly and then it can still be
you know fall somewhere else but the the
end point is is that spot true and then
in that way if somebody says no I'm not
even going to give this the time of day
as soon as it says anything that could
be construed as anti vaccine I'm gonna
say it's bad well that's bias that would
then filter out that part of it somebody
is willing to look at it and sort of see
the these studies that do and don't meet
certain criteria
the end goal there is also to be able to
get some amount of kind of consensus is
the right word but to at least see where
the the science points and you can go
out again as deep as you want and read
the designs of their study if you feel
so inclined if your is your focus if you
could choose between them would you
rather focus on the scientific part or
the politics part simply focusing this
hour on the politics part and my gut
like what I want you to focus on is the
politics part because it's really
important right now right this year
specifically but what is your focus what
is it you want our field culture I mean
I I think in my mind they're they're
linked in a way that can't be pulled
apart because the politicians talked so
much about what climate change says this
is I just say that an economist say this
and we start to say I hope they're right
there's this part where they it does
have to happen sort of in the same
system I think the election part is a
bit easier to reach because I as Eric
said there's some amount of you can just
collect the the content do a little bit
of assessing it to make it useful and to
sort of show people a summary
here I think you're not thinking big
enough either over you it's not about
policy it's not about science it's about
cleaning up the entire
information ecology is what it's
actually about right so this goes
everywhere those fingers go into
absolutely everything so I all me begin
with politics because let's face it
right it's a stink there
Ryan there's no shortage and mess to
clean up in their area but finally clean
up politics politics touches everything
right the economy and all the parts of
that and business and into I think
politics is the way it is because of the
absolute filthy nature of the entire
information ecology allows them to get
away with the that they get away
with right have you know any better we
don't know how to call them out on it
though you know I I yes I sort of agree
but I see it as the other way around I
think everything feeds into politics
rather than politics no yeah I think
politics is sort of a summary of because
you guys it does all the things that
people care about which are all these
different topics politicians try to
touch on them just to get people for
putting for them
politics feeds off of that huge
information yeah I mean this actually
has the potential if this if this really
got going like Wikipedia did you know me
if this becomes like Wikipedia then this
has the potential to absolutely smash
the entire system of politics as we
understand it you know the party
affiliations and these these Yepsen you
know it can actually be a policy by
policy evaluation voting would be out
the window right there that consensus
would be reached through this network of
information exchange and validation and
purification right all the
would be discarded and then the best
course of action would be I think very
often pretty clear once you discard all
the and all that's left is
what's what's important and real there's
a parent the best course of action will
be I think pretty obvious a lot at the
time
that's my helper and I can answer this
for him but he can't so initially I'm
gonna focus on the US and Canada cuz
that's what I know and it's an English
the only language I speak but the end
goal is to have this be global
to have this touch every country that
needs you know some help with arranging
its
every school yeah in every scale from
down to like the local you know vote
voting for people on your City Council
all the way up to voting for you know
the president or the leader edge like
with your soul
okay if you can put the information in
and what one of the things we haven't
touched on that Eric kind of was like
the power of this even in a little way
in our current political system when
this gets big enough or something like
it gets big enough and we're able to up
vote our questions to politicians
we're the ones who focus the
conversation commedia right if i think
you right so they don't answer it you
assume they don't agree with you you
assume that they're anti climate if they
haven't talked about it right so if we
up vote them and they all have to answer
it that's not gonna happen when there's
40 people on the site when there's a
million people on this site and they're
like hey you didn't answer these a no
answer is a is a negative answer yeah
for the there's so many parts that we
didn't talk about because it's so easy
to things but on the election part
that's a huge part of it is the
community can decide on what the
important election issues are then they
go and gather content to support it but
the ideal thing is that the actual
politician or their team responds and
say here's the official response from
that team here's a video yours links to
the website here's all the stuff and
then like well this person hasn't
replied yet but here's four videos we
have of them talking at a campaign rally
they all seem to say the same thing
click that you know it's at least still
consistent and we have a basic idea of
where they stand on that topic and then
the community can vote things up and
down and sort of say these election
issues are for a certain topic you've
said you care about this topic these are
probably be the election issues that you
care about but to your point Jubilee if
the media is ignoring a certain topic at
the end of the day you can say hey
politician you know three million people
want to answer to this question who's
going to answer it is the earth flat we
need to know you're from Stephan stuff
that you didn't answer it's clear that
the earth is flat what
so there are the two sides to it there's
if they've ever talked about it we'll
have some record and the community can
say they've said they think that the
earth is round okay cool but still have
those videos as proof in case the person
gives a different answer yes I think the
elders round okay but we have 38 videos
of you saying it's flat so what was up
with that because it is there is this
like information ecology where it's easy
to get I've been a nun not the Flat
Earth campaign because I watched those
documentaries I'm like there's not an
ounce of truth here there's at least
some truth and a lot of conspiracy
theories I do not know what this is but
it is not truth but anyway
it's not based on science none of the
experiments work but there's other ways
where I am on that other but I'm like
the world thinks one way and I am like
you haven't looked into it and so you
aren't actually having a conversation
based on understanding and I want tools
like this to be able to say hey here's
the actual science and here are these
things I'm word passed them in apart I'm
really bad at keeping time um so what is
how was this for you and what could be
improved what was good
um I mean it was good it was nice to
sort of you know get some my feedback
and had people chatting and have Eric's
insight and it was helpful to have
somebody that had never heard a wiki
election before cuz Jubilee you you
can't have talked for hours on this
topic so you already had a bunch of
existing knowledge it was useful to come
in and sort of have to pitch the idea
and have somebody that came from a clean
slate of like I've never had having
heard that and the initial questions of
like how do you verify the content and
that sort of thing to actually have to
go through it I do find that we sort of
scrolled on certain topics and and went
super deep and I don't think we've
really touched on many of the
aspirations I think it was a lot of it
was trying to vet out certain certain
topics and the community and Eric so I
had the did a lot of the same questions
trying to understand it more deeply is
the key though isn't it the the
gathering and sifting and quality
control of the information it's nice the
whole thing yeah and to your point like
we didn't get into so many areas where
my end goal it's not politics or science
it's to solve misinformation yeah it's a
fight it's anybody can try and attack
things on and say well actually it's
this it's that okay well we have 38,000
pieces of evidence that say to the
contrary go prove all them wrong - yeah
I just want to say that I think that is
the of your first aspiration that that
is that the message you focus on is the
information ecology even if it's this
piece is the start of it yeah it's like
word or is it on the 2020 election um my
suggestion would be or maybe not even
suggestion whatever um how can we
empower you to do this or how can what
would be your if someone was to step
forward and help you in this what would
be the biggest way your wish and also
yeah um I mean short term I'm not great
at that's you know part of the
storytelling and sort of like the the I
guess four broad strokes
I'm better at sales that in marketing so
I can have a one-on-one conversation if
people can ask questions and and there's
that back and forth pretty much everyone
I've had that conversation with seems to
get the idea and seems to like it
it's the the marketing piece where it's
having that kind of one-sided
conversation at a mass scale to get
people interested for both the the
community part just people who want to
say like yeah I'd be interested in you
know being asked some questions in to
you know help figure out how it can sell
these problems but then also build that
community that's okay with actually
pitching in to pay for the yeah yeah
developers and hosting costs and so on
oh you put your idea to practice will
you go to WikiLeaks for help or other
funders WikiLeaks might be actually a
really great funder well this cannot be
one of the person or one person
undertaking right yeah it absolutely can
the end goal is to use crowdfunding like
it can't be one like it definitely can't
be a corporation like a for-profit
corporation because that instantly
there's so much distrust there the end
goal is for like initially Kickstarter
and patreon will it be sort of the two
and then eventually just direct
donations like there's money but there's
also people right people who want to put
in stuff into the system it would be
helpful for you to have a weekly
conversation not with me but like this
online where people could join and offer
like hey where we were like kind of like
what we're doing for together to let's
to have some sort of a regular meetup or
multiple meetups where it becomes like a
project like any other so and that will
look like I'm not sure how much you've
been on patreon that's one of the really
common things that patrons get is that's
kind of like a weekly or a monthly
meetup where you can talk about it and
discuss it and the challenge is when to
sort of like say you have to have
contributed X to participate in this is
we want feedback from as many people as
possible whether it's future thinkers
future thinkers hats like a back end
where they people pave like fifty bucks
a month they have one with Dora Bates
Bateman tomorrow or the next day or
sorry next week and like you don't get a
participate on camera unless you've paid
but you can watch it anyway right you
can and I'm sure they started with
everything being free and then has later
became that because this idea of it
happening later well it's already 2020
and the elections already happening and
select betting pull on board to say hey
how does this movie how do we move this
forward how do we actually create like
what Eric said and very beta what would
what would we have the biggest impact in
the 2020 election not so that the
Democratic skeptic the Democrats get
elected open please oh but so the the
truth is out there right so we could see
what would be the most impactful for
both or at least the lies are exposed
even if the truth is now and just to
give like a really basic summary of
here's what as far as we know we think
is true like here's what Trump and the
eventual didn't true or the evidence
points or just here's what information
is available on each of these people
stances on this topic and if there's a
common theme great show that if there's
a conflict show that yeah all right the
part that didn't get touched
that is another part that could go
deeper is sort of the education layer on
top of all of it so if you're gonna be
assessing science you know and it says
is there a a double-blind study some
amount that says why that's important in
politics if you're voting for mayor
because here's what the mayor does
here's what rights they have here's what
you know types of things they can do and
here's what the general population
thinks like what sort of skill sets dish
should have so you can compare that to
what you're voting for okay so we're
gonna say goodbye to YouTube because
you've been on for an hour 10 minutes
I'm getting better at getting it closer
to the hour mark on my ones and and then
I'm actually so bye YouTube thanks for
hanging out join us next week for J
cousins project I actually don't know
what it is he hasn't gone back but we'll
be doing this again next week thank you
thanks everyone